Newspaper Guild of Albany, Local 34; Records apap005
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Newspaper Guild of Albany, N.Y., Local 34 Records
1936-1989
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap005
5.0 cubic ft.
Chartered in 1934, as the Tri-City Newspaper Guild of Albany, Schenectady, and Troy, the Guild signed its first contract with the Albany Times Union in 1937. The collection includes correspondence, minutes, contracts, and organizing files. The majority of material in the collection is photocpied.
Administrative History
The Newspaper Guild of Albany, N.Y., Local 34 was chartered on March 20, 1934, as the Tri-City Newspaper Guild of Albany, Schenectady, and Troy, N.Y. as well as nearby cities. In 1937, the Guild won its first agreement and the first Newspaper Guild agreement in upstate New York when it signed a contract with the Albany Times-Union. The Albany Guild's last strike in 1964 formed the basis for The Ink Truck, the first published novel of William Kennedy, who was one of the strikers. The local began as a union of reporters and editors, but over the years other newspaper occupations have been organized as the Guild has subsumed independent unions. Currently, janitors and drivers, as well as employees from the business office and sales and circulation departments are represented by the guild. Although the Guild has confined most of its activities to the tri-cities, it has opened offices in Hudson and Glens Falls, N.Y.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains predominantly photocopies of correspondence, executive board and membership minutes, unit minutes, bulletins, contracts, a small number of grievance files, and organizing and litigation files. There are a small number of original documents, especially in the contracts series.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into six topical file series.
Acquisition Information
The vast majority of items in this manuscript group were loaned to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Newspaper Guild of Albany, Local 34 and subsequently preservation photocopied as a part of the Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., Labor History Project. The originals were returned to Local 34. In September 2025, Ken Crowe donated 30 cu. ft. of original records, including what are likely originals of the previously photocopied materials plus new materials dating to the 2010s.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of a small number of files noted in series 3, Grievance Files.
Newspaper employees -- Labor unions -- New York (State).; Journalists -- Labor unions -- New York (State).; Newspaper publishing -- New York (State) -- Albany.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Albany.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Glens Falls.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Hudson.; Minutes; Correspondence; Newsletters; Contracts; Labor; Albany, New York; Schenectady, New York; Rensselaer County, New York; American Newspaper Guild.; Independent Committee of the Albany Times Union.; American Newspaper Guild.; Newspaper Guild of Albany, N.Y.; Kennedy, William, 1928- Ink truck.
- Minutes, 1936-1987; 1; 1 cubic ft.
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1936-1946 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 1)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1947-1952 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 2)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1953-1962 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 3)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1963-1965 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 4)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1966-1969 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 5)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1970-1975 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 6)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1976-1978 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 7)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1979-1984 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 8)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1985-1987 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 9)
  - Glens Falls Unit Meeting Minutes, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 10)
  - Knickerbocker News Unit Meeting Minutes, 1942-1956; 1966 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 11)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1936-1946 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 12)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1947-1951 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 13)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1952-1957 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 14)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1958-1961 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 15)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1962-1967 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 16)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1968-1973 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 17)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1974-1977 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 18)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 19)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1980-1983 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 20)
  - Times Union Unit Meeting Minutes, 1942-1951 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 21)
- Organizing and Litigation Files, 1936-1989; 2; 1.6 cubic ft.
  - Capital Newspapers - Injunction Against Chester W. Vanderbilt, Pres. Local 34 (Strike Initiation), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Capital Newspapers - NLRB Case (Interference with Union Activity), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Capital Newspapers - NLRB Case on Bylines, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Capital Newspapers - NLRB Charges, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Glens Falls - Newspaper, Inc., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Glens Falls Newspapers and Albany Printing Pressmen, Assistants and Offset Workers No. 23 - Contract, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Glens Falls - NLRB (1 of 2), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Glens Falls - NLRB (2 of 2), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Glens Falls - NLRB Case (1 of 2), 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Glens Falls - NLRB Case (2 of 2), 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Glens Falls - NLRB Case, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Glens Falls - Organizing, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Glens Falls - Organizing, 1973; 1978; 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Glens Falls - Organizing, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hudson Unit - Decertification, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hudson Unit - NLRB Case Unfair Labor Practice, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Knickerbocker News - Circulation NLRB Petition, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Knickerbocker News - Circulation Organizing, 1950; 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Knickerbocker News - Circulation Organizing, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Knickerbocker News - Editorial Employees NLRB Petition, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Knickerbocker News - NLRB Case, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Knickerbocker News - NLRB Case, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Knickerbocker News - NLRB Charges, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Knickerbocker News - NLRB Charges, Scott Wanhope Case, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Knickerbocker News - NLRB Commercial, 1942; 1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Knickerbocker News - NLRB Petition, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Knickerbocker News - NLRB Petition, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Knickerbocker News - Organization, 1947; 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Knickerbocker News - Press Circulation Union Contracts, 1950-1951; 1953; 1956; 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Merger - Knickerbocker News and Times-Union, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Non-Communist Affidavits, 1950; 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Organizing - General, 1952; 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Press Co. Merger - NLRB Charges (1 of 2), 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Press Co. Merger - NLRB Charges (2 of 2), 1937-1941 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Saratoga Organizing, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Schenectady Gazette Organizing, 1937-1939; 1954; 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Schenectady Organizing, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Schenectady Sun, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Schenectady Union Star - Organizing, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Times Union Circulation Independent Committee Contracts, 1944-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Times Union Circulation Independent Committee NLRB Charges, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Times Union Circulation NLRB Case, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Times Union Circulation NLRB Charges, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Times Union Circulation NLRB Petition, 1938; 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Times Union Circulation Organizing, 1944-1947 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Times Union Circulation Organizing, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Times Union Independent Committee Organizing, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Times Union NLRB Petition, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Troy Record and Times Record Organizing, 1946; 1948; 1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Troy Record Organizing, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Union Star, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Union Star Organizing, 1958; 1965-1966; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Grievance Files, 1952-1982; 3; 0.2 cubic ft.
  - Bulletin Board Problem, 1976 (Box 1 (3-Grievance Files), Folder 1)
  - Funiciello, John--Grievance, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Grievance Files), Folder 2)
  - Graphics Editor--Grievance, 1976; 1981-1982 (Box 1 (3-Grievance Files), Folder 3)
  - Grievance Procedure, 1952-1953 (Box 1 (3-Grievance Files), Folder 4)
  - Kniskern, Paul--Grievance, 1982 (Box 1 (3-Grievance Files), Folder 5)
  - Riley, George--Grievance RESTRICTED, 1959 (Box 1 (3-Grievance Files), Folder 6)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Rosenblatt, Linda A.--Grievance RESTRICTED, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Grievance Files), Folder 7)
  - Scott, Janet--Grievance, 1953-1954 (Box 1 (3-Grievance Files), Folder 8)
- Subject Files, 1936-1989; 4; 0.6 cubic ft.
  - 1957 Contract with Albany Times-Union (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1964-1967 Contract with Capital Newspapers Div., The Hearst Corp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1967-1970 Contract with Capital Newspapers Div., The Hearst Corp., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1970-1973 Agreement with Capital Newspapers Division, The Hearst Corporation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1979-1982 Contract with Capital Newspapers, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1982-1985 Agreement with Capital Newspapers Division, The Hearst Corporation, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1985-1988 Agreement with Capital Newspapers Division, The Hearst Corporation, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1988-1991 Contract with Capital Newspapers, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bulletins, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bulletins, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bulletins, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bulletins, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bulletins, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins, 1975-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - By-Laws, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Guild International Convention Program, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Page One Ball Programs, 1958-1959; 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, 1964; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Taken through a court window at Troy, County Court..., 1964
    - Taken outside of New York Supreme Court Judge T...., 1964
    - Taken outside of New York Supreme Court Judge T...., 1964
    - Taken during recess at the injunction hearings..., 1964
    - On November 29, 1964, union members attend a...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - On November 29, 1964, union members attend a...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Picket line during the 1964 strike of the...
    - Newspaper Guild of Albany Strike, 1964
    - Newspaper Guild of Albany Strike, 1964
    - Newspaper Guild of Albany Strike with William Kennedy, 1964
    - Newspaper Guild of Albany Strike, 1964
  - Photographs, Undated (Flat-file 1)
  - Scrapbook Pages, 1936-1940; 1964; Undated (Flat-file 2)
- President's Files, 1941-1976; 5; 0.6 cubic ft.
  - Albany AP Guild Unit, Minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild, Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Associated Press, Organizing, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Capital District Industrial Union Council, CIO, 1942-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Empire State District Council Convention in Albany, NY, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Empire State District Council, Minutes, 1952; 1963; 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Empire State District Council, Minutes, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Empire State District Council, Minutes, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Greater New York Industrial Union Council, CIO, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Guild Reporter, Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Guild Reporter, Correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Independent Committee of the Albany Times Union, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Inter-Union Cooperation, 1962; 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Legislation, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Membership and Committee Lists, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, Pension Fund, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Guild of Rochester, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Organizing, ca. 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Political Action Committee, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Political Action Committee, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Strike Steering Committee, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Veterans, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Veterans, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Wire Service, 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Empire State District Council Records, 1942-1960; 6; 1.0 cubic ft.
  - A.P. Organizing, 1951-1952; 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Affiliation, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Newspaper Guild - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Newspaper Guild - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Newspaper Guild - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report and Recommendations, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Apprentice Training, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Associate Membership, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bargaining Conference, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Binghamton Sun, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Binghamton Sun - Complaint, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Binghamton Sun Contract, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Buffalo Newspaper Guild, Local 26, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bulletins of Empire State District Council, ANG, 1947-1948; 1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - By-Laws, 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Capital District and Troy Area Industrial Councils, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cleveland Newspaper Guild, Local 1, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Convention, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Convention, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), 1942-1948; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), 1942-1948; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Empire State District Council, ANG, 1947-1949; 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Empire State District Council- Meeting, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gannet Chain, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gannet Conference of Guilds, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gannett Pensions, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hearst Chain Council, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hearst Chain Council, 1947-1952; 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Kingston Newspaper Guild, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1945-1948; 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Monthly Reports of International Representative, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Negotiations, 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - New York State CIO Council, 1951-1952; 1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newburgh-Beacon News, Contract Negotiations, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newburgh-Beacon News, Organizing, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Newsletter of Empire State District Council, ANG, 1953; 1957; 1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Guild of Rochester, Local 17, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Regional Institute, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Syracuse Newspaper Guild, Local 143, 1945-1946; 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Syracuse Newspaper Guild, Local 143, 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Syracuse Post-Standard, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Training Institute, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Utica Newspaper Guild, Local 129, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Utica Observer Dispatch, Contracts, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 6)